# CURRICULUMN VITAE OF SPHIWE JOE MASILELA



### **PROFILE**

Certified in Information and Communication Technology specializing in Software and Systems Development.

Experienced in I.T Operations, Project Delivery and Management. I also possess intermediate knowledge in I.T Security Threat Analysis, Detection as well as, Management, along with User Identity, Access Management capabilities and SIEM engineer abilities.

Adapting, learning new systems, method application or tools and processes is one of my key strengths for If I do not know something I will learn it.

### **CONTACT**

PHONE:

(+27) 79 614 3418

LINKEDIN:

https://www.linkedin.com/in/sphiwe-masilela1214/

EMAIL:

masilsj@outlook.com

ADDRESS:

Johannesburg, Gauteng, South Africa

### **SKILLS**

### SOFT

Agile Methodology
Customer Concierge Mindset
People Skills
Task Ownership and Delivery
Attention to Detail and Quality
Complex problem-solving
Resilience, stress tolerance and
flexibility
Active learning and learning strategies
Sign Language (SA)

### **TECHNICAL**

C# and C++ Coding SQL Database and Server Knowledge Troubleshooting and Linux Analytical thinking and innovation Technology use, monitoring and control Technology design and programming

# **EDUCATION**

### Wits University of the Witwatersrand Advanced Project Management Certification

2019 January - December

Modules: Strategic Project Management, Managing Project Integration, Managing Project Risk, Managing Project Quality, Project Communication and Procurement.

# Project Management Institute Business Management Certificate

2018 January - December

Modules: Strategy Implementation, Evaluation and Control, Environmental Analysis, Organizational Goals and Values, Sustainable Competitive Advantage.

# Tshwane University of Technology Software Development National Diploma

2014 January - 2017 December

Major Modules: Development Software, Information Systems, Technical Programming, Computing Systems, Computing Skills, Computing Fundamentals.

## Vaal University of Technology Computer Literacy Certification

2013 January – December

Modules: Mathematics, Keyboard Skills, Computer Fundamentals, Language Literacy.

# MICT SETA – DVG Media Center Systems Development National Certificate

Modules: HTML and CSS, SQL Server, ASP.Net, ICT Skills, Internet, and Business Concepts

### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# McKinsey & Company [Junior I.T Solutions Advisor]

2017 - 2019

**Duties:** Managed I.T Front Desk Operations, IT Equipment Administration, Office Network Support, Incident Logging, Escalation and Resolving, Printer Setup and Management, VoIP Support, Application and Software Remote Support, Mobile Phone Configuration, Server Room and Meeting Rooms Support.

**Success Projects**: I.T Storeroom Administration and Clean-Up, Office Printer configuration and management, Laptop and Mobile Phone Migration, SIM Card Migration, Mail Server Upgrade. Deliver insightful I.T Inductions for New-Hires. Achieved a successful Server room cabling clean-up and management. Succeeded in handling the VOIP phone setups for the new office.

# IBM South Africa [I.T Security Specialist – Expert Labs] 2019 – 2021

**Duties: IBM QRadar SIEM** - Administration (Roles, Security Profiles and Authentication), QRadar Applications Management and Updates, QRadar License Pool Management, Asset Discovery Scans, QRadar Rules Fine-tuning, Threat Analysis with Watson.

**IBM Identity and Access Management** - Security Access Management (Advanced Access Control, Access Manager Federation), IBM Security Identity Manager (Update User Data). Protect IT Assets Using Risk-Based and Multi-Factor Authentication, Secure User Identities and Deliver Convenient Access. Unify Access Control and Security for On-Prem and Cloud Platforms. Enforce Mobile Access Control Policies.

# **CERTIFICATIONS/BADGES**

- Excel Intermediate certification
- Business Management HC
- JavaScript and HTML certificate
- Developing Ethical Hacking tools with Python
- Fundamentals to Cybersecurity Architecture
- Identifying Web-based
   Attacks through logs
- Intermediate coding using Python
- Cyber Threat Intelligence
- Introduction to PowerShell scripting
- MITRE ATT&CK Defense for CTI
- Networking fundamentals for Security Practitioners
- Privileged Access Management
- Protect Sensitive Data Against Threats
- Security & Privacy by Design
- Containers & Kubernetes
- Identify & Investigate Cyber Threats
- Agile Explorer
- Design Thinking Practitioner
- Data Science & Analytics
- Coding Introduction
- Cybersecurity Introduction
- Think Like a Hacker

**Success Projects:** Client Center QRadar SIEM Management, SARS IAM Management (Creating User Group Policies, Modigying Existing User Access and Allocating New Users the appropriate Group, Deleting Users and halting access).

### Performanta South Africa [Junior SIEM Engineer]

2022 -- Present

**Duties: IBM QRadar SIEM, QRoC and Encore** – Collaborating to Deploy and maintain SIEM on-premises and components to collect logs from clients' on-premises systems and cloud platforms, Perform regular health checks on SIEM components.

Working with clients to ensure that log sources (Windows/Linux servers, databases, firewalls, VPN, web proxy, mail gateway, IPS, cloud platforms, custom logs) feed into the SIEM.

Provide advice and support to clients on how to configure log sources to send events to SIEM. Work with client IT personnel to configure their log sources.

Verify log sources feed into the SIEM correctly and Upgrade SIEM components as needed.

Assess log coverage and identify gaps where it would be useful to onboard security events to improve coverage and detection capability. Develop, test, implement and fine-tune rules to detect suspicious, malicious or abnormal activity that may indicate an attack or security policy violation in client environments.

Develop reports and dashboards as per client requirements, and extract data from SIEM so that it can be analyzed in external systems.

Perform Log Source health checks and cleanup by diagnosing or disabling and deleting Log Sources for clients upon request.

## **REFERENCES**

### McKinsey & Company

EMEA I.T Global Help Desk Africa I.T Team Leader Miss. Kabelo Magabane (+27) 81 463 9751

### IBM South Africa

Digital Trust Sales Leader - MEA IBM Global Markets – Cloud & Cognitive Solutions Sales Mr. Makgama Leornard Langa (+27) 81 040 3764

### Performanta South Africa

Managed Security Services Executive SIEM Engineering Manager Mr. Peter du Preez (+27) 64 521 4162